<appendix id="lessappendix"> <title>Unsettled Business</title>

<para>Lojban is a young language, but a language which prides itself on being fully and 
explicitly documented... but not always. In a couple of instances, topics alluded to in 
these lessons are still somewhat up in the air. Though what the lessons themselves
say about Lojban grammar you can rely on, there are some side issues on which the 
dust has not yet settled. This appendix covers two issues in particular; you do not
need to go through this on your first reading of the lessons, but once you start
reading, writing, and speaking Lojban, this appendix tries to explain some things you 
may bump into, and which might strike you as odd.</para>

<sect1 id="lessAvoha"><title>Embedded <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase></title>

<para>In <link linkend="less8">Lesson 8</link>, we said that <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase> refers back to <quote role="gloss">the first
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> of this <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase></quote>. This is all well and good when 
your sentence only contains one <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase>. But when it doesnt &mdash; and it often 
doesn't &mdash; we have a problem. In

<informalexample><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la kris. djuno ledu'u la pat. prami vo'a</foreignphrase></para>

</informalexample>does <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase> refer to <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la kris.</foreignphrase> (<quote>Chris knows that Pat loves 
her</quote>), or <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la pat.</foreignphrase> (<quote>Chris knows that Pat loves 
herself</quote>)? In 

<informalexample><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la kris. djuno ledu'u la pat. prami la djun. soi vo'a</foreignphrase></para>

</informalexample>does <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase> swap <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la djun.</foreignphrase> with <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la pat.</foreignphrase> (<quote>Chris knows that Pat loves 
June and vice versa, that they love each other</quote>), or with <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la kris.</foreignphrase> (<quote>Chris knows that Pat loves 
June, and June knows that Chris loves Pat</quote>)? </para>

<para>The answer will, perhaps, shock you. In both cases, <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase> is acting as what is called in linguistics a
reflexive: it refers back to something in the same sentence. In natural 
languages, reflexives almost always refer back to subjects; and in Lojban, the  
x1 place is as close as you will get to a subject. The difference is, when you
have this kind of embedding, the reflexive can refer back to the subject of the
verb it is immediately tied to (<firstterm>short-distance reflexive</firstterm>),
or it can refer all the way back to the subject of the entire sentence 
(<firstterm>long-distance reflexive</firstterm>.)</para>

<para>Now, <wordasword>herself</wordasword> in English is a short-distance reflexive: 
if Chris knows that Pat loves herself, then Chris knows that Pat loves Pat, not 
Chris. Reflexives in almost all languages are short-distance; relatively few languages 
allow their reflexives to be long-distance as well as short-distance (Chinese),
or have long-distance reflexives distinct from short-distance (Icelandic). So if <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase> corresponds to <wordasword>herself</wordasword>, 
then it too is short-distance.</para>

<para>And here, we have some unfortunate confusion. <citetitle>The Complete Lojban 
Language</citetitle> describes <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase> as short-distance. But the earlier material
defining the language had it as <emphasis>long</emphasis>-distance; and that is in fact 
how just about all Lojbanists use it.</para>

<para>Why would Lojbanists do something seemingly so perverse, and contrary to how
most languages work? Basically, because their attitude towards pro-<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> is quite different to normal language attitudes 
towards pronouns. Lojbanists would like to have unambiguous pro-<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> &mdash; pro-<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> whose reference can be determined with 
certainty. Now, to do a short-distance reflexive's job (refer to something in the same 
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase>, you can very often use 
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ri</foreignphrase> instead of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase>. But to do a long-distance reflexive's 
job (refer to something in the main <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase> of the sentence), <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ri</foreignphrase> usually will not do the job, because you will have 
mentioned other <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> in 
between. This leaves you stuck with <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ra</foreignphrase>, which is deliberately as vague as natural
language pronouns. <quote>But,</quote> reasons the average Lojbanist, <quote>if I 
wanted natural language
vagueness, I'd be speaking a natural language. And because I will need to refer back to 
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> of the main sentence 
often (main and embedded <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase> tend to 
involve the same cast of characters), I'd rather <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase> serve as an unambiguous way of doing just that.</quote></para>

<para>So whether because it was what they got used to in 1991 (and they didn't want to 
relearn the language in 1997), or because they thought <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase> would be more useful that way, Lojbanists interpret <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la kris. djuno ledu'u la pat. prami la djun. soivo'a</foreignphrase> 
as saying that Chris knows that Pat loves <emphasis>her</emphasis>, not herself. So 
Lojbanists use <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase> long-distance.</para>

<para>... almost always. There are two occasions when they sometimes use short-distance 
interpretations instead. The first is when the long-distance interpretation doesn't 
make sense for some reason. For example, the x<subscript>1</subscript> place of the main <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase> contains the embedded <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase> containing <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase> &mdash; so a long-distance reading would get
terribly recursive: <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">lenu la suzyn. jmina fi le vo'a ctebi cinta cu 
cinri</foreignphrase> makes sense as <quote>Susan putting on her lipstick is
interesting</quote>, but not as the horridly recursive <quote>Susan putting on 
<wordasword>x</wordasword>'s lipstick is interesting</quote> &mdash;
where <wordasword>x</wordasword> is <quote>Susan putting on 
<wordasword>x</wordasword>'s lipstick</quote>,
where <wordasword>x</wordasword> is <quote>Susan putting on 
<wordasword>x</wordasword>'s lipstick</quote>,
where <wordasword>x</wordasword> is <quote>Susan putting on 
<wordasword>x</wordasword>'s lipstick</quote>...)</para>

<para>The second occasion is (you guessed it) <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">soivo'a</foreignphrase>. People are used to thinking of 
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">soivo'a</foreignphrase> as <foreignphrase 
lang="lat">vice versa</foreignphrase>, which forces a short-distance 
interpretation. And while there are reasons you would want <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase> in general to be a long-distance reflexive, 
there isn't much occasion for a long-distance reciprocal.</para>

<para>If usage to date were the only thing that determined the meaning of Lojban
words (as is usually believed by the community), we might say that <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase> is <emphasis>by default</emphasis> 
long-distance, but becomes short-distance under special circumstances (such as 
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">soivo'a</foreignphrase>.) But past usage is not the 
only factor in determining what Lojban words mean. Lojbanists cherish their
precious few unambiguous pro-<foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>, and most would rather not lose one.
So, while some Lojbanists have said (and will likely continue to say) things like
<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la kris. djuno ledu'u la pat. prami la djun. soi vo'a</foreignphrase>, 
meaning that Pat and June love each other, most Lojbanists think they are being
wrong, and would prefer something like <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la kris. djuno ledu'u la pat. prami la djun. soi <emphasis>ri</emphasis></foreignphrase>.</para>

<note><para>The phrase <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la djun. soi ri</foreignphrase> counts as one <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>, so thankfully <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ri</foreignphrase> here does not refer to June!</para></note>

<para>Incidentally, there are truly unambiguous alternatives to <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase>, if you're not comfortable with the way this
is heading. We won't explain them here, but you might be able to guess how they work anyway.
The guaranteed short-distance reflexive in Lojban is <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">lenei</foreignphrase>, and the guaranteed long-distance reflexive
is <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">leno'axiro</foreignphrase>. (<foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">leno'a</foreignphrase> is enough when there is only one level of <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase> nesting.) In the unlikely case your use of <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">vo'a</foreignphrase> is met with blank, uncomprehending stares,
you can try using these instead.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="lessAcehu"><title>Unfilled places in <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ka</foreignphrase>-abstractions</title>

<para>When there is no <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase> in the abstraction, there is some controversy
as to how the <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ka</foreignphrase>-abstraction is to
be interpreted. In many instances, the existence of a slot to be filled by 
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase> is required by the definition of 
the <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase> itself. For example,
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sisku leka pensi</foreignphrase> makes no sense, unless 
you are looking for a specific something that fits a <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase> slot in <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">pensi</foreignphrase>.</para>

<para>For such instances, the location of
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase> is ambiguous, and <citetitle>The
Complete Lojban Language</citetitle> mentions no
convention having arisen, like with <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ke'a</foreignphrase>, on where it goes by default. The current
default assumption is that <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase> here behaves like <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ke'a</foreignphrase>, and occupies the first empty place.
This means that, while 
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le ka xlura</foreignphrase> without <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase>
can potentially mean both <quote role="gloss">influence</quote> and <quote
role="gloss">susceptibility</quote>, the default assumption is that it means <quote 
role="gloss">influence</quote>, while <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le ka se xlura</foreignphrase> means <quote role="gloss">susceptibility</quote>. Likewise, <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le ka 
xendo</foreignphrase> can usually be assumed to mean <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le 
ka ce'u xendo</foreignphrase> <quote role="gloss">the property of people being 
kind</quote>, and probably not <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le ka xendo fi 
ce'u</foreignphrase> <quote role="gloss">the property of an action being
something in which kindness is shown</quote> (although that action 
<emphasis>is</emphasis> frequently what is meant in English by 
<wordasword>kindness</wordasword>.)</para>

<para>A more contentious issue is, whether this should hold for all <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ka</foreignphrase>-abstraction, wherever they may occur. For
example, does <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi tavla leka xendo</foreignphrase>
mean the same thing as <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi tavla leka ce'u xendo zo'e 
zo'e</foreignphrase>? Are you saying you are talking about kindness, as a property 
specifically applied to the person showing the kindness?</para>

<para>The majority view as of this writing is yes. This means that <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ka</foreignphrase> is treated the same, whether it appears as a
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> of <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">sisku</foreignphrase> or <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">tavla</foreignphrase>.</para>

<para>The catch is, when <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ka</foreignphrase> was originally invented, <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase> didn't exist yet. And the original definition 
of <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ka</foreignphrase> refers not to properties
at all, but to qualities.</para>

<para><wordasword>Property</wordasword> and <wordasword>quality</wordasword> are
fairly abstract, as words of English go, so this may not seem to make any difference. 
However, the objection that has been raised is that <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ka</foreignphrase> shouldn't always be regarded as singling out one or 
two places. The quality of kindness, it is argued, does not single out the person
being kind, or the person to whom the kindness is shown (which is what a property
does.) Instead, it concentrates
only on the <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase> of the 
relationship: what it means to say that a relationship of kindness holds, whoever
is involved in it.</para>

<para>This view is not universally held; at least some of the Lojbanists who think 
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ka</foreignphrase> is all about being a property
of something specific, think this notion is better expressed instead by <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">si'o</foreignphrase>, the abstractor defined as <quote 
role="gloss">idea, concept</quote>.</para>

<para>Talk at this level of abstraction is not something you're likely to run into
the moment you start using Lojban. It does explain, however, why you'll see 
<wordasword>property</wordasword> used a lot here, but <wordasword>quality</wordasword> 
a lot elsewhere. It may also explain why you will see some grown Lojbanists blanch
at the sight of a <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase>...</para>

</sect1>

</appendix>