<chapter id="less15"><title>Singled out: Isolating specific places</title>

<para>In this lesson, we look at three features of Lojban grammar which
normally get relegated to the <quote role="socalled">too-hard</quote>
basket. Each of them involves singling out a particular <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> from a <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase>, as being somehow more special than
the other <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>. The full 
logical machinery associated with these <quote role="socalled">singlings 
out</quote> can get rather formidable, which is why Lojbanists tend to 
regard these features with some degree of awe. Hopefully we'll present 
these concepts to you with a minimum of fuss, so you can go about using 
them comfortably in your Lojban.</para>

<sect1 id="less15kau"><title>Indirect questions</title>

<para>A Lojban question word is a request to <quote>fill in the
slot</quote>, <emphasis>wherever</emphasis> it appears in a sentence. So
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis>ma</emphasis> cilre la
lojban.</foreignphrase> is the question <quote><emphasis>Who</emphasis> is
learning Lojban?</quote> And by the same token, <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mi djica lenu <emphasis>ma</emphasis> cilre la
lojban.</foreignphrase> is the question <quote>I want
<emphasis>who</emphasis> to learn Lojban?</quote> &mdash; or, in actual
English (since English likes to have its question words at the start of the
sentence), <quote><emphasis>Who</emphasis> do I want to learn
Lojban?</quote> And <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mi pu cusku lesedu'u <emphasis>ma</emphasis> cilre la
lojban.</foreignphrase> is <quote>I said <emphasis>who</emphasis> is 
learning Lojban?</quote> &mdash; i.e. <quote><emphasis>Who</emphasis> did 
I say is learning Lojban?</quote></para>

<para>There's no reason <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">du'u</foreignphrase> should behave any differently than
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">nu</foreignphrase>, let alone
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sedu'u</foreignphrase>; so <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mi djuno ledu'u <emphasis>ma</emphasis> cilre la
lojban.</foreignphrase> means <quote>I know that <emphasis>who</emphasis>
is learning Lojban?</quote> &mdash; i.e. <quote><emphasis>Who</emphasis> do
I know is learning Lojban?</quote></para>

<para>What it does not mean is <quote>I know who is learning 
Lojban</quote> &mdash; as in <quote>I know the identity of the person 
learning Lojban.</quote> In a construction like that in English, you are 
not asking a real question; that's why this is called an <emphasis>indirect 
question</emphasis>. Instead, you 
are saying that you already <emphasis>know</emphasis> the answer to the 
question. You can tell the word <wordasword>who</wordasword> in that statement is 
not a request for information, because it is not at the start of the 
sentence, there's no question mark (or questioning intonation), and the 
question word is not being emphasised.</para>

<para>Lojban does not use any of these workarounds; a question word is a
question word in Lojban, anywhere it happens to end up. This means that
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi djuno ledu'u <emphasis>ma</emphasis>
cilre la lojban.</foreignphrase> can never be an indirect question: it is
asking for an answer (even if you're doing it rhetorically, though that is
the kind of behaviour which Lojbanists &mdash; a level-headed bunch by most
accounts, at least when they're speaking in Lojban &mdash; might not
necessarily appreciate.) So what to do?</para>

<para>Well, let's look at what you do know. Let's say the person learning 
Lojban is Fred. If I ask you the question <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ma cilre la lojban.</foreignphrase>, you know what value 
to fill in the <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ma</foreignphrase> slot 
with: <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">la fred.</foreignphrase> So you 
could just say <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi djuno ledu'u la fred. 
cilre la lojban.</foreignphrase> For whatever reason, however, you're not 
telling me the actual name &mdash; totally within your prerogative. In 
fact, I could say about you that <quote><emphasis>You</emphasis> know who 
is learning Lojban</quote> &mdash; but because I don't know it, I'd have no name 
to fill in the slot with.</para>

<para>So you know that <emphasis>someone</emphasis> is learning Lojban:
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">do djuno ledu'u da cilre la
lojban.</foreignphrase> And you can fill in the value of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">da</foreignphrase>, even though I can't. What we want is
some word that would tell us <quote>the answer that goes here isn't being
said, but it is known anyway.</quote> That word is the UI <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">cmavo</foreignphrase>, <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">kau</foreignphrase>. So <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mi djuno ledu'u da <emphasis>kau</emphasis> cilre la
lojban.</foreignphrase> means <quote>I know someone is learning Lojban, and 
I know who it is.</quote> <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">do djuno ledu'u da <emphasis>kau</emphasis> cilre la
lojban.</foreignphrase> means <quote>You know someone is learning Lojban, and 
<emphasis>you</emphasis> know who it is.</quote></para>

<para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">kau</foreignphrase> says that the value of the word it 
attaches to is known &mdash; whatever that word is. So in fact, you can put 
it next to a question word, and it will cancel out the question word's 
force. <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mi djuno ledu'u <emphasis>ma kau</emphasis> cilre la
lojban.</foreignphrase> means exactly the same as <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mi djuno ledu'u <emphasis>da kau</emphasis> cilre la
lojban.</foreignphrase> &mdash; and has the advantage of looking just like 
the indirect questions we're already familiar with.</para>

<para>Since <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">kau</foreignphrase> belongs to
<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">selma'o</foreignphrase> UI, you can place it pretty much anywhere. In
particular, anywhere you can put a question word in Lojban, you can make it
an indirect question by adding <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">kau</foreignphrase>. So you can say
<quote>I know how many people are learning Lojban</quote>, as
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi djuno ledu'u <emphasis>xo
kau</emphasis> prenu cilre la lojban.</foreignphrase> (Remember,
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">xo</foreignphrase> is the question word
for numbers.) You can even make indirect questions of Lojban's more exotic
question words. For example, in <link linkend="less11">Lesson 11</link>,
the waiter asks Jyoti and Susan <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">lanme je'i
bakni</foreignphrase> <quote>lamb or beef?</quote> Once they answer, he
knows whether they want to eat lamb or beef; in Lojban, 

<informalexample><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ba'o lenu la djiotis. .e la suzyn. spuda kei le sabji cu
djuno ledu'u ra djica lenu citka loi lanme <emphasis>je'i kau</emphasis>
bakni</foreignphrase></para></informalexample>

</para>

<simplesect role="vocab"><title>Vocabulary</title>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">farna</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is the
direction of x2 (object/event) from origin/in frame of reference
x3</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">gunro</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1
rolls/trundles on/against surface x2 rotating on axis/axle x3; x1 is a
roller</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">rokci</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is a
quantity of/is made of/contains rock/stone of type/composition x2 from
location x3</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sepli</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is
apart/separate from x2, separated by partition/wall/gap/interval/separating
medium x3</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">simsa</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is
similar/parallel to x2 in property/quantity x3 (ka/ni); x1 looks/appears
like x2</para></listitem></varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</simplesect>


<simplesect role="exercise"><title>Exercise 1</title>

<para>Express the following indirect questions in Lojban. Use Lojban question 
words to translate the English question words.

<orderedlist>

<listitem><para>I want to know when you will talk to me.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>I don't know why you won't talk to me.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>I've said who I thought was a fool.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Tell me where the beer is.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>You said who I should give the book to.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Tell me how does it feel when you're on your own with no 
direction known like a rolling stone. (Not only is there a profusion of 
Dylan here, but this is kind of a trick question. But do translate it as an 
indirect one, anyway.)</para></listitem>


</orderedlist>


</para>
</simplesect>



</sect1>

<sect1 id="less15cehu"><title>Properties</title>

<para>We have seen, here and there, instances of Lojban expressions of
properties. Lojban treats properties as abstractions, introduced by
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ka</foreignphrase>. There is nothing
controversial about that; properties are things you can talk about
(<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>), which involve
relationships and characteristics (<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase>.) So if <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">xendo</foreignphrase> means <quote 
role="gloss">kind</quote>, for instance, <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le ka xendo</foreignphrase> refers to <quote 
role="gloss">kindness</quote>.</para>

<para>The thing about properties, though, is that they are properties
<emphasis>of</emphasis> something. They are associated, not just with a
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase>, but with a
particular place of the <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase>. For instance, if I am being kind
(<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi xendo</foreignphrase>), then I can
talk about <emphasis>my</emphasis> kindness (<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le ka <emphasis>mi</emphasis> xendo</foreignphrase>.) If
Fred is being kind, we would instead speak of <emphasis>Fred</emphasis>'s
kindness (<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le ka <emphasis>la
fred.</emphasis> xendo</foreignphrase>.)</para>

<para>Now, consider influence and susceptibility. Both involve the
relationship expressed in Lojban as <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">xlura</foreignphrase>: <quote role="gloss">x1 (agent)
influences/lures/tempts x2 into action/state x3 by influence/threat/lure
x4</quote>. So the Lojban for influence is <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le ka xlura</foreignphrase>. And the Lojban for
susceptibility is... <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le ka
xlura</foreignphrase>? No, that can't be right. Let's try again. Influence
is the property associated with the x1 of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">xlura</foreignphrase>, the influencer. Susceptibility is
the property associated with the x2 of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">xlura</foreignphrase>, the influencee. I need to somehow,
in the abstraction, highlight the place I'm interested in: <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le ka <emphasis>mi</emphasis> xlura</foreignphrase> is my
influence, while <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le
ka <emphasis>mi</emphasis> se xlura</foreignphrase> is my susceptibility. 
I could play tricks like using whichever place comes first, or whichever place is empty 
first, to tell which place I'm concentrating on. But that would just be a 
convention; and as was the case with relative clauses and <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ke'a</foreignphrase>, you'd want some way of explicitly 
spelling out what place you're concentrating on. Moreover, what happens if 
both candidate places are filled &mdash; is <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le ka mi xlura do</foreignphrase> my influence over you, 
or your susceptibility to me? Who are we concentrating on here?
</para>

<para>The solution Lojban presents is pretty similar to relative clauses
and <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ke'a</foreignphrase>, as it turns out.
(Some logicians would think of it as identical, in fact.) It's also similar
to Lojban's approach to questions. Remember in <link
linkend="less13">Lesson 13</link> that the search for extraterrestial
intelligence was, in terms of Lojban, a search for the value to fit in the
slot <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">leka ___ terdi bartu
pensi</foreignphrase>. By the same token, influence is a property of things
that fit into the x1 place of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">xlura</foreignphrase>; so you can think of influence as
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">leka ___ xlura</foreignphrase>. (If we
know that <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi</foreignphrase> fits into the
slot, we have <quote role="gloss">my influence</quote>; if we know that
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">la fred.</foreignphrase> fits into the
slot, we have <quote role="gloss">Fred's influence</quote>.) And
susceptibility is a property of things that fit into the x2 place of
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">xlura</foreignphrase>; so you can think of
susceptibility as <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le ka xlura
___</foreignphrase> (or <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le ka ___ se
xlura</foreignphrase>.)</para>

<para>Lojban has a word for that slot associated with properties. It isn't
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ma</foreignphrase>, because you're not
asking someone what fills the slot; you're just pointing out that there's a
slot there that can be filled. It isn't <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ke'a</foreignphrase> either, because <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ke'a</foreignphrase> refers back to something you've
already expressed as a <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> (though you might think of a
relative clause as a property belonging to that <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>.) Property slots get their own KOhA
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">cmavo</foreignphrase>, <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase>. So influence is <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le ka ce'u xlura</foreignphrase> <quote>the property 
that X influences</quote>: anyone or anything that
has that property can stand in for <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase>. Susceptibility is <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le ka xlura ce'u</foreignphrase> <quote>the property 
that [something] influences X</quote>, or <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le ka ce'u se xlura</foreignphrase> <quote>the property 
that X is influenced</quote>: anyone or anything
that has <emphasis>that</emphasis> property can stand in for <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase>. And extraterrestial intelligence is
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le ka ce'u terdi bartu
pensi</foreignphrase> <quote>the property that X is an earth-exterior 
thinker</quote>: you can tell whether you've found your Little Green
Men by substituting them for <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase>, and seeing if the <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase> is true (<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le ka <emphasis>lo fange pe la vulkan.</emphasis> cu terdi
bartu pensi</foreignphrase>.)</para>

<note><para>If you:

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>did Computer Science at University,
<emphasis>and</emphasis> you didn't skip Theory of Computation in third
year just because it had all sorts of strange Greek letters and ivory tower
mathematics in it;</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>did Computer Science at
University, and skipped Theory of Computation in third year, but hacked
around with LISP a lot anyway;</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>did
Linguistics at University, and did not run screaming from the Formal Semantics elective 
in third year (if you were even offered it)
just because it had all sorts of strange Greek letters and more mathematics
than you were used to (i.e. none);</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

then it will mean something to you that <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase> is a lambda variable, and that
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le ka ce'u xlura da de di</foreignphrase>
corresponds to &lambda;<wordasword>x</wordasword>.<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">xendo</foreignphrase>(<wordasword>x</wordasword>,<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">da</foreignphrase>,<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">de</foreignphrase>,<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">di</foreignphrase>). The rest of you (which includes 90%
of all programmers and 99% of all linguists) can go ahead and forget I ever
mentioned this.

</para></note>

<para>When there is no <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase> in the abstraction, the location of
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase> is ambiguous, and no
convention has arisen as with <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ke'a</foreignphrase> on where it goes by default. The x1
place (whether occupied or not) seems as good a default as any, but that
should probably be left up to usage to determine. This means that
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le ka xlura</foreignphrase> on its own
means both <quote role="gloss">influence</quote> and <quote
role="gloss">susceptibility</quote>, although <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le ka se xlura</foreignphrase> may well end up the
preferred way of saying <quote role="gloss">susceptibility</quote>.</para>

<para>What happens if you want to put <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase> in the abstraction, but the place
you're concentrating on is already occupied, because you know who it's a
property of? Well, in that case you want to say that the value already
there takes up the space where the slot would be. If <quote
role="gloss">kindness</quote> is <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le ka
ce'u xendo</foreignphrase>, <quote role="gloss">my kindness</quote> is
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le ka ce'u xendo fa mi</foreignphrase>.
This means that both <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase>
and <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi</foreignphrase> take up the x1 of
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">xendo</foreignphrase>. A somewhat less
painful way to do this is to use <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">po'u</foreignphrase> to say that the property slot and
the value filling it are basically the same thing: <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le ka ce'u po'u mi xendo</foreignphrase> <quote>the
quality of X, namely me, being kind.</quote></para>

<note><para>The infinitesimal number of you that know about lambda calculus
are by now thinking this is a pretty lame way of implementing
beta-reduction. All I can say to that is, if you want LISP, you always know where 
to find it...</para></note>

<note><para>The quantity abstractor, <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ni</foreignphrase>
<quote role="gloss">the amount by which...</quote> can also take <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase>. Had we actually looked at <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ni</foreignphrase> in this course at all, this piece of 
information might have been slightly more useful to you.</para></note>

<simplesect role="vocab"><title>Vocabulary</title>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ckire</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is
grateful/thankful to/appreciative of x2 for x3
(event/property)</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mamta</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is a
mother of x2; x1 bears/mothers/acts maternally toward x2; [not necessarily
biological]</para></listitem></varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</simplesect>


<simplesect role="exercise"><title>Exercise 2</title>

<para>Express the following qualities in Lojban, using <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase> explicitly in all cases.

<orderedlist>

<listitem><para>Gratitude</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Similarity to Arnold Schwarzenegger</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Motherhood</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Having a mother</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>My similarity to Arnold Schwarzenegger</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Being a place where people get anxious; creepiness (Hint:
Use <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti
tcita</foreignphrase>.)</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

</para>
</simplesect>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="less15tuha"><title>From <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> to abstraction: <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">tu'a</foreignphrase></title>

<para>When looking up words in a <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">gismu</foreignphrase> list, you will have already noticed
that, where languages like English has people or things as subjects or
objects, Lojban often uses abstractions instead as places of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">gismu</foreignphrase>. For example, in
English, you say that <emphasis>someone</emphasis> is interesting, or
<emphasis>something</emphasis> is interesting. In Lojban, you aren't really
meant to say either. The definition of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">cinri</foreignphrase> is <quote role="gloss">x1
(abstraction) interests/is interesting to x2; x2 is interested in
x1</quote>. In other words, as far as Lojban is concerned, it's not things
or people that are interesting, but <emphasis>actions</emphasis> or
<emphasis>properties</emphasis> involving those things or people. For
example, Jyoti cannot be said to be interesting simply by virtue of being
Jyoti; the way Lojban puts it, it's the things Jyoti does (or is) that are
interesting &mdash; the way she talks about British sitcoms, her choice of 
headgear, her tendency to break into '80s songs after she's had a few 
drinks. (Oh, I forgot to tell you about all that. Maybe next course.)</para>

<para>The same goes for <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">fenki</foreignphrase> <quote role="gloss">crazy</quote>.
In almost every language, it is people that are called crazy. Only occasionally
are actions also called crazy. Lojban defines <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">fenki</foreignphrase> as <quote role="gloss">x1
(action/event) is crazy/insane/mad/frantic/in a frenzy (one sense) by
standard x2</quote>. In other words, as far as Lojban is concerned,
craziness lies in actions, not in people; a crazy person is by definition
someone who does crazy actions. (And this means that someone suffering from
the particular forms of mental illness loosely called <quote
role="socalled">crazy</quote> wouldn't be called <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">fenki</foreignphrase> in Lojban &mdash; since their
condition is not <emphasis>primarily</emphasis> a matter of socially
unaceptable actions &mdash; but rather <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">menli
bilma</foreignphrase>: <quote role="gloss">mentally ill</quote>.)</para>

<para>For now, you may be prepared to accept this as an endearing quirk of
Lojban. (If you're not, we explain why Lojban is all topsy-turvy like this
in the next section.) But very often, you have no idea what to say is
the <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase> of that 
abstraction, or you don't particularly care to. For example, yes, Jyoti 
doing this, that and the other is what is interesting about her; but I may 
not know first-hand what exactly her particular talents are, or I may not feel 
like going into a five-minute spiel every time I merely want to point out 
that she is interesting. If I can't say the Lojban for <quote>Jyoti is 
interesting</quote>, I should at least be able to say something like 
<quote>Jyoti {doing some stuff I'm not listing here} is 
interesting</quote>, or <quote>Some things about Jyoti are 
interesting.</quote> In other words, I have to say <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">lenu la djiotis. cu ___ cu cinri</foreignphrase>, but I 
shouldn't have to fill in that slot with an explicit <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase> each time.</para>

<para>There are slots in Lojban sentences that we have in fact been leaving
empty all the time. Remember <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">zo'e</foreignphrase>? <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">zo'e</foreignphrase> is the <quote role="socalled">don't
care</quote> value we leave implied in the places of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase> we leave empty. For example, when I
say <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi klama le barja</foreignphrase>, I'm
not bothering to specify my point of origin, route, or vehicle. They are
all implied to be <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">zo'e</foreignphrase>
(<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi klama le barja zo'e zo'e
zo'e</foreignphrase>): there is a point of origin, a route and a vehicle
involved, but we don't really care what they are.</para>

<para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">zo'e</foreignphrase> is a
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>; but it has a
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase> equivalent,
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">co'e</foreignphrase>. <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">co'e</foreignphrase> can appear where any <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase> can appear, but it leaves the
particular relationship involved between its <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> unspecified. So <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mi co'e le barja</foreignphrase> means something like
<quote>I thingummy the bar</quote>: the bar and I are in some relationship,
but I'm not bothering to say what it is. I might be going to it, coming
from it, sleeping in it, refurbishing it, or hearing about my neighbour
getting drunk in it once. It just doesn't matter enough for me to say
what.</para>

<para>Now normally, you can't get away with this: if you leave out the
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase> in your story, you
pretty much have no story. But with these abstractions that we wish weren't
really abstractions, <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">co'e</foreignphrase>
is just what you need: you can get away with making an abstraction
containing only the <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>
you want to talk about. You don't have to specify
<emphasis>anything</emphasis> else in the abstraction &mdash; especially
not the <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase>. So if I
want to say <quote>Jyoti is interesting</quote>, I need only say
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">lenu la djiotis. cu
<emphasis>co'e</emphasis> cu cinri</foreignphrase>. I'm still saying an
abstraction involving Jyoti is what is interesting, so I'm following the
requirements of the <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">gismu</foreignphrase>
list. But that's all I'm saying; what particular abstraction it is that is
interesting, I am leaving entirely open. In the same way, if I want to say
<quote>Zhang is crazy</quote> (or <quote>berserk</quote>, probably a closer
translation of <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">fenki</foreignphrase>), I
don't have to enumerate the various wacky stunts he has pulled over the
years. I can simply say that <quote>some stuff about Zhang is
crazy</quote>, which in Lojban comes out as <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">lenu la jang. co'e cu fenki</foreignphrase>. The value of
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">co'e</foreignphrase> could be
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">dasni [loi zirpu]</foreignphrase>
<quote>wears purple</quote>, <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">dansu [la
zgikrfanki jipci]</foreignphrase> <quote>dances the Funky Chicken</quote>,
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">tavla [bau la lojban.]</foreignphrase>
<quote>speaks Lojban</quote>, or whatever; we're just not bothering to name
it here.</para>

<para>Lojban can go one better, though. As you can tell, Lojban is going to
have you saying <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">lenu ___ cu co'e
kei</foreignphrase> quite often (and you never know when you might need that
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">kei</foreignphrase> terminator); so it
offers you an abbreviation: <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">tu'a</foreignphrase>. <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">tu'a da</foreignphrase> means <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">lenu da cu co'e kei</foreignphrase>; so you can translate
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">tu'a</foreignphrase> as <quote>some
abstraction associated with...</quote>, or more colloquially, <quote>some
stuff about...</quote> <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">tu'a</foreignphrase> is easily the most popular way of
dealing with abstractions you wish weren't there in Lojban; Lojban
sentences using it come out fairly similar to the natural language
sentences <emphasis>without</emphasis> abstractions we're used to seeing.
So the usual Lojban for <quote>Jyoti is interesting</quote> is
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis>tu'a</emphasis> la djiotis.
cinri</foreignphrase>, and the usual Lojban for <quote>Zhang is
crazy</quote> is <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis>tu'a</emphasis>
la jang. fenki</foreignphrase>.</para>

<simplesect role="vocab"><title>Vocabulary</title>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">djica</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1
desires/wants/wishes x2 (event/state) for purpose
x3</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">cfari</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1
[state/event/process] commences/initiates/starts/begins to occur;
(intransitive verb)</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">fanza</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 (event)
annoys/irritates/bothers/distracts x2</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">nelci</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is fond
of/likes/has a taste for x2 (object/state)</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">snuti</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1
(event/state) is an accident/unintentional on the part of x2; x1 is an
accident</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">troci</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1
tries/attempts/makes an effort to do/attain x2 (event/state/property) by
actions/method x3</para></listitem></varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</simplesect>


<simplesect role="exercise"><title>Exercise 3</title>

<para>Some of these sentences need to be translated in Lojban with <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">tu'a</foreignphrase>, and some don't. Supply the 
appropriate translation, in either case.

<orderedlist>

<listitem><para>I tried the curry.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>I wanted the curry.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>I liked the curry.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>My leaving was accidental.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Gratitude annoys me.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Curry annoys me.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The irritation has begun.</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

</para>
</simplesect>


</sect1>

<sect1 id="less15jai"><title>Raising: <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">jai</foreignphrase></title>

<warning><para>This section is long and complicated. On the plus side, 
it's also the final section in the course.</para></warning>

<para>Things weren't always like this. In the '80s, the ancestor of Loglan
still said that things were interesting, and people were crazy, just like
most normal languages, and without detouring through abstractions. So what
happened?</para>

<para>Well, what happened was that Lojbanists noticed how linguists have
been analysing these concepts in natural languages, and how they were
coming up with their own versions of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase>. (The word, by the way, is
<wordasword>predicates</wordasword>; we've been avoiding it up to now, but
we think you can handle the truth from now on...) Often, what was a noun in
one part of the sentence, and a verb in another part, were brought together
and considered to be underlyingly part of the same abstraction
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>.</para>

<para>A good example is the phrase <wordasword>I am difficult to
annoy</wordasword> in English. At first sight, you might think that
<wordasword>I</wordasword> is a <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> of
<wordasword>difficult</wordasword>. And grammatically it is: it's the
subject. But logically it isn't: what we're describing as difficult is not
<wordasword>me</wordasword>. We can't say <quote>Who is difficult?</quote>
&mdash; <quote>Me (to annoy)</quote> What's actually going on is that,
underlyingly, what is difficult is <wordasword>to annoy me</wordasword>:
the action of getting me annoyed is what is hard to achieve &mdash; not me!
This is why English also allows you to say <wordasword>It is difficult to
annoy me</wordasword>, and (if you squint a little) <wordasword>To annoy me
is difficult</wordasword>. And sure enough, Lojban expresses this concept
according to that <quote role="socalled">underlying</quote> form:
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">lenu fanza mi cu nandu</foreignphrase>
<quote>The event of annoying me is difficult</quote>.</para>

<para>So why did English pull that wierd switcheroo with <wordasword>I am
difficult to annoy</wordasword>? Basically, because when we talk, we aren't
concentrating in our minds on intangible abstractions like <quote>the event
of annoying me</quote>, let alone <quote>the state of Jyoti having certain
unspecified properties.</quote> Instead, we run little stories in our head,
with heroes and villains: concrete heroes and villains &mdash; people, for
the most part. And as it happens, we make the subjects of our sentences be
the heroes and villains we're concentrating on. (That's what a subject's
ultimate job is: to present what we're concentrating on.) So by pulling a
switcheroo like that, we're not talking about abstractions and events any
more; the subject of the sentence is now our perenially favourite subject
&mdash; namely <emphasis>me</emphasis>: it's <emphasis>me</emphasis> that 
is difficult to annoy. (Yes, it <emphasis>is</emphasis>
all about me...) This process is called in linguistics
<wordasword>raising</wordasword>, because it raises concrete subjects (and
objects) we want to talk about, out of the haziness of an abstraction
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> (or <quote
role="socalled">argument</quote>, to use English logical
terminology.)</para>

<para>Once the requisite number of Lojbanists did an undergraduate course
in syntax (you may commence throwing darts at effigies of Nick Nicholas at
your leisure), it was realised that there were a <emphasis>lot</emphasis>
of <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">gismu</foreignphrase> whose place
structures contained both a raised concrete <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> (usually x1), and an abstraction
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> itself
containing the first <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>.
For example, the place structure of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">fenki</foreignphrase> used to be <quote>x1 is crazy
in behaviour x2 (abstraction) by standard x3.</quote> But
<emphasis>any</emphasis> abstraction that would go into x2 would contain
the x1 <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>: any crazy
behaviour would automatically be the behaviour of the crazy person. For
example, you'd get <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">la jang. fenki lenu la
jang. dasni loi zirpu</foreignphrase>; <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">la
jang. fenki lenu la jang. dansu la jipci</foreignphrase>; <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la jang. fenki lenu la jang tavla bau la
lojban.</foreignphrase> The question then became: does the x1 tell us
anything the x2 wasn't already telling us? We'd know who was involved in
the crazy behaviour, because that person would be a <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> inside x2. Was there any reason to 
accord the person an extra place in the overall <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase>? The decision was, no: behaviour is what 
is crazy, so you can work out that the person acting out the behaviour is 
the crazy person. There's no need to have an extra place for the person, 
when you can already work out who they are. The same conclusion was arrived 
at for <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">cinri</foreignphrase>: it is 
abstractions &mdash; events and qualities &mdash; that attract interest; 
and an interesting person is simply a person involved in an interesting 
attraction.</para>

<para>All well and good; but natural languages do raising for a reason.
So when Lojban has its <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">gismu</foreignphrase> 
without raising, it gains in eliminating redundancy and logical muddledness; 
but it loses in <quote role="socalled">naturalness</quote>. We like 
talking about people rather than abstractions in our languages; and Lojban 
should not go out of its way to form an exception to this.</para>

<para>There is a solution of sorts to all this using <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">tu'a</foreignphrase>; but it doesn't actually do what
raising does in natural languages: it doesn't <emphasis>change</emphasis>
the x1 place from an abstraction to a concrete <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>. And there are times you will want
to do just that. One example is joining <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase>-tails. In English, you can say
<quote>Jyoti is interesting and beautiful.</quote> This is
based on two sentences (<wordasword>Jyoti is interesting</wordasword>,
<wordasword>Jyoti is beautiful</wordasword>) which have the same
subject. So we can easily combine them into a single sentence. In Lojban,
the equivalent sentences are <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">tu'a la
djiotis. cinri</foreignphrase> and <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">la djiotis. 
melbi</foreignphrase>. There is no way you're going to
join those two <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase>
together with <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">gi'e</foreignphrase>: they
simply do not have their first <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> in common. But they're both 
somehow <quote role="socalled">about</quote> Jyoti; so you really should be 
able to work around this.</para>

<para>An even more important instance when you want raising is in forming
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> out of this kind of
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">gismu</foreignphrase>. A <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> means whatever goes into the x1 of
its <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase>. So if
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">la djiotis. ninmu</foreignphrase>, then I
can describe Jyoti as <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">lo
ninmu</foreignphrase> <quote role="gloss">a woman</quote>; if
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">lemi karce cu xe klama le gusta fu
mi</foreignphrase>, then I can describe <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">lemi karce</foreignphrase> as <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">lo xe klama</foreignphrase> <quote role="gloss">a
vehicle</quote>. So how do I say that someone is a cheat, or a deceiver?
The <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">gismu</foreignphrase> for <quote
role="gloss">deceive</quote>, <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">tcica</foreignphrase>, has the place structure <quote
role="gloss">x1 (event/experience)
misleads/deceives/dupes/fools/cheats/tricks x2 into x3
(event/state)</quote>. So, while in English we say that x1 deceives x2 into
doing x3, by doing x4, in Lojban the person and the action are merged into
the one place. That makes <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">lo tcica</foreignphrase>
a trick, not a trickster. To say that someone is a trickster or a cheat,
we need to use <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">tu'a</foreignphrase>:
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">tu'a da tcica</foreignphrase>. But you
can't put <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">lo</foreignphrase> in front of
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">tu'a da</foreignphrase>: the deceiver
would have to be the x1 of some <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase>, in order to get their own
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>.</para>

<para>The solution to this is to force Lojban to have raising after all,
changing its place structure by modifying the <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase> involved &mdash; just as
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">se</foreignphrase> changes the place
structure of its <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase>,
swapping its first and second place. If we put <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">jai</foreignphrase> in front of a <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">selbri</foreignphrase>, its x1 place changes from an
abstraction, to any <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>
contained <emphasis>within</emphasis> the abstraction. Let's try this with 
a few sentences:

<informalexample>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem> 
<para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis>lenu la jang.
dasni loi zirpu</emphasis> cu fenki</foreignphrase> </para> </listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis>la jang.</emphasis> cu jai fenki</foreignphrase>
</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>
<para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis>lenu la djiotis. cu 
co'e</emphasis> cu cinri</foreignphrase>
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis>la djiotis.</emphasis> cu jai 
cinri</foreignphrase>
</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>
<para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis>tu'a la 
ranjit.</emphasis> tcica la suzyn.</foreignphrase>
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis>la ranjit.</emphasis> jai 
tcica la suzyn.</foreignphrase>
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis>lenu fanza mi</emphasis> 
cu nandu</foreignphrase>
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis>mi</emphasis> jai nandu</foreignphrase>
</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</informalexample>
</para>

<para>You'll notice that, with these new place structures, the Lojban
phrases sound pretty much like their English equivalents: <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la djiotis. cu jai cinri</foreignphrase> corresponds to
<wordasword>Jyoti is interesting</wordasword>, <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la ranjit. jai tcica la suzyn.</foreignphrase> to
<wordasword>Ranjeet deceives Susan</wordasword>, and so forth.</para>

<para>We can now do with <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">jai</foreignphrase> those things we couldn't before. The
Lojban for <quote>Jyoti is interesting and beautiful</quote>, for example,
is <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">la djiotis. cu jai cinri gi'e
melbi</foreignphrase>. That's because Jyoti goes in the x1 place of
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">jai cinri</foreignphrase>, just as it goes
into the x1 place of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">melbi</foreignphrase>. And if I want to make a
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> meaning <quote
role="gloss">deceiver</quote> or <quote role="gloss">trickster</quote>, I
can use <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">jai</foreignphrase> to do it:
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis>tu'a la ranjit.</emphasis>
tcica</foreignphrase> &rArr; <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis>la
ranjit.</emphasis> jai tcica</foreignphrase> &rArr; <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la ranjit. me <emphasis>lo jai
tcica</emphasis></foreignphrase>. </para>

<para>However, <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi jai
nandu</foreignphrase> does <emphasis>not</emphasis> correspond to <quote>I am difficult to
annoy.</quote> In switching a concrete <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> for the original x1 &mdash; the
abstraction that was difficult &mdash; we have lost the abstraction: there
is nothing in <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi jai nandu</foreignphrase>
that means <quote role="gloss">to annoy</quote>. But not to worry: Lojban
allows you to keep the original abstraction in the <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase> by preceding it with <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">fai</foreignphrase>. <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">fai</foreignphrase> is a <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">cmavo</foreignphrase> like <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">fa</foreignphrase> and <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">fe</foreignphrase>; it effectively adds a new place to
the <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">bridi</foreignphrase>. So <quote>I am
difficult to annoy</quote> is matched almost word-for-word by the Lojban
sentence <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi jai nandu fai lenu fanza
mi</foreignphrase>. And we can apply this pattern further afield; for
example, <quote>the book took three months to write</quote> is in Lojban
properly <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">lenu finti le cukta cu masti li
ci</foreignphrase> <quote>to write the book had a month duration of
three</quote>; raising allows the slightly more familiar-looking
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le cukta cu jai masti li ci fai lenu
finti</foreignphrase>.</para>

<para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">jai</foreignphrase> has not proven
as popular as <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">tu'a</foreignphrase>,
presumably because it involves a fairly thorough rearrangement of place
structures &mdash; and has the whiff about being somehow <quote
role="socalled">un-Lojbanic</quote>. But as we've seen, it allows you to
talk about things in a way that is in many ways more natural; and though it
belongs to <quote role="socalled">advanced</quote> Lojban, it is a feature 
you will find it useful to be familiar with.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="less15summary"><title>Summary</title>
<para>In this lesson, we have covered:

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Indirect questions (<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">kau</foreignphrase>)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Property variables (<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase>)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Raising (<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">co'e, tu'a, jai,
fai</foreignphrase>)</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

And with that, we have reached the end of the <citetitle>Lojban for 
Beginners</citetitle> course! There are several bits of the grammar of 
Lojban not covered here; but you now have the essentials with which to 
start using Lojban, and you are in a good position to pick up the rest 
&mdash; preferably from <citetitle>The Complete Lojban 
Language</citetitle>, which is a fairly easy read for a reference grammar. 
Moreover, most of the Lojban you will see will stick fairly closely to the 
grammar covered here. <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">.i .a'o do se zdile tu'a le ve ctuca gi'e ba gleki lenu 
pilno la lojban</foreignphrase>

</para>

<simplesect role="vocab"><title>Vocabulary</title>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">birti</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is
certain/sure/positive/convinced that x2 is
true</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">cipra</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1
(process/event) is a test for/proof of property/state x2 in subject x3
(individ./set/mass)</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">cizra</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is
strange/weird/deviant/bizarre/odd to x2 in property x3
(ka)</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">curmi</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 (agent)
lets/permits/allows x2 (event) under conditions x3; x1 grants privilege
x2</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">dicra</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 (event)
interrupts/stops/halts/[disrupts] x2 (object/event/process) due to quality
x3</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">drata</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 isn't
the-same-thing-as/is different-from/other-than x2 by standard x3; x1 is
something else</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">drani</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is
correct/proper/right/perfect in property/aspect x2 (ka) in situation x3 by
standard x4 (Note: when people say correct things, that does not
automatically make them <quote
role="socalled">correct/proper/right/perfect</quote>)</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">jarco</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 (agent)
shows/exhibits/displays/[reveals]/demonstrates x2 (property) to audience
x3</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">kucli</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is
curious/wonders about/is interested in/[inquisitive about] x2
(object/abstract)</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">kumfa</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is a room
of/in structure x2 surrounded by partitions/walls/ceiling/floor x3
(mass/jo'u)</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">logji</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1
[rules/methods] is a logic for deducing/concluding/inferring/reasoning
to/about x2 (du'u)</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">lo'u... le'u</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>Quotation 
marks like <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">lu... li'u</foreignphrase>, used when the Lojban text 
contained in them doesn't make grammatical sense.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mebri</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is a/the
brow/forehead [projecting flat/smooth head/body-part] of
x2</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">remna</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is a
human/human being/man (non-specific gender-free sense); (adjective:) x1 is
human</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">rufsu</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is
rough/coarse/uneven/[grainy/scabrous/rugged] in
texture/regularity</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sonci</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is a
soldier/warrior/fighter of army x2</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">tarci</foreignphrase></term><listitem><para>x1 is a
star/sun with stellar properties x2</para></listitem></varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</simplesect>

<simplesect role="exercise"><title>Exercise 4</title>

<para>Translate from Lojban.

<orderedlist>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">.i le vo pendo na djuno le du'u ri zvati ma kau mu'i ma 
kau</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">.i la jang. cusku lu .i mi cazi ckire da'i tu'a loi glare cnino bo se 
zbasu ckafi li'u</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">.i la djiotis. se cinri leka ce'u cizra pe le kumfa poi 
ri nenri</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">.i la suzyn. cusku lu .i
.ue le vi canko noi jarco tu'a loi tarci cu pe'i jai se xanka
li'u</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">.i la ranjit. cusku lu .i go'i fa ji'a le re fange noi 
jarco leka le mebri po'e ce'u cu rufsu li'u</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">.i pa fange poi simsa lo sonci cu jai cfari fai lenu 
lanli le terdi pendo kei gi'e cusku lo'u .uxrup .ua. doglau. latl.
tcak val tca. le'u</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">.i la ranjit. kucli ledu'u le fange cu tavla bau ma kau</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">.i le ka tu'a ce'u se kucli cu se jundi le drata fange 
noi cusku zoi gy. Greetings people of the planet ... um... Saturn?
gy.</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">.i la jang. cusku lu .i tu'a le fange na drani so'a da li'u</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

</para>
</simplesect>

<simplesect role="exercise"><title>Exercise 5</title>

<para>Translate into Lojban. Use <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ce'u</foreignphrase> in quality abstractions. Use <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">jai</foreignphrase> instead of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">tu'a</foreignphrase> wherever possible.

<orderedlist>

<listitem><para>Susan says <quote>Excuse me, but I think you are uncertain 
about where you are &mdash; which is Earth.</quote></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The alien says <quote>You are correct.</quote></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><quote>We are, uh, merely testing you for terrestial 
intelligence.</quote></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Jyoti says <quote>You could have done that and not have
interrupted our dancing.</quote></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ranjeet says <quote>And also, if you knew that we are 
terrestial people and intelligent, then you also knew that we are 
terrestial intelligences.</quote> (Use forethought connectives.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The alien says <quote>Are you the radio 
transmitter?</quote></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ranjeet says <quote>I am one of the radio transmitters.</quote></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><quote>But <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mi po'onai cradi</foreignphrase> is more logically 
correct.</quote></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The alien frowns, says <quote>You are allowed to 
leave</quote>, and un-removes the friends from the dance 
hall.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The alien says <quote><foreignphrase lang="art-klingon">xu&stress;m&akl;n 
&stress;m&ekl;q&length;oq. &stress;w&ekl;d&zhkl;pux</foreignphrase></quote>, which is 
translated as <quote>Human logic. Yuck.</quote></para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

</para>
</simplesect>


</sect1>

<sect1 id="less15answers"><title>Answers to exercises</title>

<simplesect role="excanswer"><title>Exercise 1</title>

<para><orderedlist>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi djica lenu mi djuno 
ledu'u do ba tavla mi ca ma kau</foreignphrase> (You can place the <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ca ma kau</foreignphrase> anywhere after <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ledu'u</foreignphrase>.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi na djuno ledu'u do na 
ba tavla mi mu'i ma kau</foreignphrase> (Same goes for <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">mu'i ma kau</foreignphrase>.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi ba'o cusku lesedu'u mi 
pu jinvi ledu'u ma kau bebna</foreignphrase> (Yes, Lojban can get prolix...)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ko cusku lesedu'u le 
birje cu zvati ma kau</foreignphrase> or <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ko cusku lesedu'u birje vi ma kau</foreignphrase> (... 
except, perhaps, where it matters most! The observative in the second 
version actually works: <quote>Beer! Tell me where?!</quote>)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">do pu cusku lesedu'u mi 
bilga lenu mi dunda le cukta ma kau</foreignphrase> <emphasis>or</emphasis> (if you want to risk 
the attitudinal) <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">do pu cusku 
lesedu'u mi .ei dunda le cukta ma kau</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>OK, this doesn't have to be that close (let alone rhyme), 
and in fact the English is closer to a direct than an indirect question, 
but this is something like <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">ko cusku fi mi fe lesedu'u pei kau do sepli gi'e na 
djuno le farna gi'e simsa lo gunro rokci</foreignphrase>. Told you this was 
kind of a trick question...</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

</para>
</simplesect>

<simplesect role="excanswer"><title>Exercise 2</title>

<para><orderedlist>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ka ce'u ckire</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ka ce'u simsa la arnold. 
cvartseneger.</foreignphrase> (or <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">la'o 
gy. Arnold Schwarzenegger gy.</foreignphrase>, if you prefer.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ka ce'u mamta</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ka mamta ce'u</foreignphrase> or <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ka 
ce'u se mamta</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ka ce'u po'u mi simsa la
arnold. cvartseneger.</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ka xanka vi 
ce'u</foreignphrase>. A little contrived, we admit.</para></listitem>


</orderedlist>

</para>
</simplesect>

<simplesect role="excanswer"><title>Exercise 3</title>

<para><orderedlist>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mi troci tu'a le cidjrkari</foreignphrase> (What you 
actually try is to eat it &mdash; or, on occasion, to keep it down.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mi djica tu'a le cidjrkari</foreignphrase>
(This usually comes as a shock to people learning Lojban, but you can't actually want 
objects, only events. The event you usually want is to be in possession of 
the object, in some way or other.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mi nelci le cidjrkari</foreignphrase>
(The <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">gismu</foreignphrase> list explicitly allows <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">nelci</foreignphrase> to involve both objects and 
events; so you don't need <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">tu'a</foreignphrase> here. This makes <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">nelci</foreignphrase> quite different to <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">djica</foreignphrase>.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">lenu mi cliva cu snuti</foreignphrase> (No surprise 
there; <quote role="gloss">leaving</quote> corresponds to an abstraction.)
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">leka ckire cu fanza mi</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">tu'a le cidjrkari cu fanza mi</foreignphrase> (Unlike 
gratitude, curry is certainly not an abstraction.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le fanza cu cfari</foreignphrase>
(Yes, you read correctly. To fit the x1 of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">cfari</foreignphrase>, a <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase> doesn't actually have to 
<emphasis>look like</emphasis> an abstraction; it just has to 
<emphasis>mean</emphasis> an abstraction. Anything that can be described 
as <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le fanza</foreignphrase> is going to be an abstraction, 
because of the place structure of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">fanza</foreignphrase>. So since the x1 of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">fanza</foreignphrase> is a state or event, and the x1 of <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">cfari</foreignphrase> is also a state or event, they can 
both be describing the same thing &mdash; without needing to strain abstractions 
out of one or the other using <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">tu'a</foreignphrase>.)</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

</para>
</simplesect>

<simplesect role="excanswer"><title>Exercise 4</title>

<para><orderedlist>

<listitem><para>The four friends do not know where they are, or why they 
are there. (You can ask more than one question in a sentence in Lojban, 
direct or indirect.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Zhang says <quote>Right now, I would be grateful for a hot, 
freshly-brewed coffee.</quote> (You are grateful in Lojban for events 
rather than objects, so fully expanded, <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">.i la jang. ckire da'i <emphasis>lenu kakne lenu 
pinxe</emphasis> loi glare cnino bo se 
zbasu ckafi</foreignphrase>.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Jyoti is interested in the wierdness of the room she is in.
(<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">pe</foreignphrase> is another way of 
associating abstractions with specific objects. Note that <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">pe</foreignphrase> follows a <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>, so the current <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">sumti</foreignphrase>, <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">leka ce'u cizra</foreignphrase>, is assumed to have been 
terminated. A fate we hope will not befall our intrepid heroes...)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Susan says <quote>Wow! This window, which shows the stars, 
is in my opinion something to be anxious about.</quote> (<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">se xanka</foreignphrase> describes an event that 
provokes anxiety, so <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">jai se xanka</foreignphrase> describes a 
<emphasis>thing</emphasis> involved in the event that provokes anxiety. 
Strictly speaking, Susan is probably misusing <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">jarco</foreignphrase>...)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ranjeet says <quote>So are the two aliens, who show that
their foreheads are rough</quote> or <quote>who exhibit roughness in their
foreheads.</quote> (... Ranjeet, of course, cannot help but be correct in
his usage of <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">jarco</foreignphrase>.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>One alien who is like a soldier starts analysing the 
Earthling friends, and says <quote><foreignphrase lang="art-klingon">&stress;&glottal;uxrup w&akl;&glottal; 
&stress;&dkl;o&gkl;l&akl;w&glottal; l&akl;&tlh; t&shkl;&akl;q v&akl;l 
t&shkl;&akl;&glottal;</foreignphrase></quote> (A lot of you may have guessed the language the alien is 
speaking. You are correct, and let's leave it at that, shall we?)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ranjeet is curious about what language the aliens are 
speaking in. (No, I haven't clued him in...)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Being an object of curiosity is something noticed by the other 
alien, who says (in English) <quote>Greetings people of the planet ... um... 
Saturn?</quote></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Zhang says <quote>Stuff about the aliens is not right in 
most regards.</quote> (In other words, there are properties 
involving these aliens that are not correct in most regards; for example, 
their sense of direction.)</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

</para>
</simplesect>

<simplesect role="excanswer"><title>Exercise 5</title>

<para><orderedlist>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">.i la suzyn. cusku lu ta'a do'u pe'i do na birti ledu'u 
do zvati ma kau po'u la terdi li'u</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">.i
le fange cu cusku lu .i do jai drani</foreignphrase> (Not
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">do drani</foreignphrase>, which would mean
<quote>You, as Susan, are a correct (or perfect) human being</quote>; it is
only one aspect of Susan, namely what she has just said, which is being
described here as correct.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">.i mi'a .y. jai cipra po'o
leka ce'u terdi pensi kei do li'u</foreignphrase> (You could say
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">.i mi'a .y. jai cipra po'o leka <emphasis>do po'u
ce'u</emphasis> terdi pensi kei li'u</foreignphrase>, because it's the person with the
quality being tested that is the test subject. But for practical reasons,
Lojban hasn't eliminated this particular redundancy, so you might as well
exploit it.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">.i la djiotis. cusku lu .i
do nu'i go'i gi'enai jai dicra lenu mi'a dansu li'u</foreignphrase> (In
Lojban, only events interrupt; latex-foreheaded aliens are <quote
role="gloss">involved in interrupting</quote>.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">.i la ranjit. cusku lu .i 
ji'a ganai do pu djuno ledu'u mi'a ge terdi prenu gi pensi gi do djuno 
ledu'u mi'a terdi pensi li'u</foreignphrase> (No, Ranjeet can never resist 
a good syllogism.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">.i le fange cu cusku lu .i 
xu do du le cradi li'u</foreignphrase> (A legitimate use of <foreignphrase 
lang="art-lojban">du</foreignphrase>, since to the alien <quote 
role="gloss">The radio transmitter</quote> and <quote 
role="gloss">You</quote> refer to the same person.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">.i la ranjit. cusku lu .i
mi me le cradi</foreignphrase> (If you want to emphasise the plurality of
the transmitters, you could say <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">.i mi me le 
su'o re cradi</foreignphrase> <quote>I am one of the two or more radio 
transmitters</quote>.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">.i ku'i lu mi po'onai
cradi li'u cu zmadu fi leka ce'u logji drani li'u</foreignphrase> (Although
a person saying something correct is not eligible to be the x1 place of
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">drani</foreignphrase>, the correct thing
that they say <emphasis>is</emphasis> eligible: <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">drani</foreignphrase> is
not by definition restricted to abstractions.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">.i le fange cu furmu gi'e
cusku lu do jai se curmi fai lenu cliva li'u gi'e to'e vimcu le pendo le
dansydi'u</foreignphrase></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">.i le fange cu cusku zoi
gy. </foreignphrase><foreignphrase lang="art-klingon">xu&stress;m&akl;n &stress;m&ekl;q&length;oq. &stress;w&ekl;d&zhkl;pux</foreignphrase> <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">
gy. noi se fanva fi lu .i remna logji .a'unai li'u</foreignphrase> (or, in
Lojban phonetic approximation, <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">lo'u xuman.
mekok. uedjpux. le'u</foreignphrase>.)</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

</para>
</simplesect>

</sect1>

</chapter>
